Inventory of the Alexander Brown Papers (1) 1815-1910
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Alexander Brown Papers (1), 1815-1910.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. Acc. 65 B83
2,949 items.
Inventory includes the letters and business papers,1815-1910, of Alexander Brown (1843-1906), farmer, merchant and author who lived in Nelson County, Virginia.
Alexander Brown
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 2,914 items, 05/06/1941.
Gift: 5 items, 05/22/1944.
Gift: 30 items, 05/09/1946.
Biographical Information
Born at Glenwood, Nelson County, Virginia, Alexander Brown was deafened while serving in the Confederate Army in the explosion of a powder-boat near Fort Fisher, N.C. He married Caroline Augusta Cabell and after her death, Sarah Randolph Cabell. He was the author of The Genesis of the United States, The First Republic in America, The Cabells and Their Kin and other works.
Scope and Content Information
Inventory contains the papers of Alexander Brown, farmer, merchant and author who lived in Nelson County, Virginia. Includes correspondence relating to his books, The Genesis of the United States, The First Republic in America, The Cabells and Their Kin and New Views, and other correspondence and business papers of Brown including letters written from Australia, England, Wales and Egypt, 1867-1869. Correspondents include Herbert Baxter Adams, Jabez Lamar Monroe Curry, Charles Deane, and Lyon Gardiner Tyler.
The collection also includes papers of Mayo Cabell and ledgers of Mayo Cabell and Co., Lynchburg, Virginia and of the Lynchburg Female Seminary; accounts of "Belmont," "Benvenue," and "Norwood" plantations (in Nelson County); and genealogical material on the Brown and Cabell families.
Organization
This inventory has been organized into ten series: 1. Correspondence of Alexander Brown; 2. Business Reciepts of Alexander Brown; 3. Business Reciepts and Papers of Various Members of the Cabell Family; 4. Papers of Mayo Cabell; 5. Papers concerning the books written by Alexander Brown; 6. Bills, Reciepts and Papers of Mayo Cabell and His Son; 7. Correspondence of Alexander Brown; 8. Miscellaneous Materials of Alexander Brown; 9. Papers of R. L. Brown, the son of Alexander Brown; 10. Page Proofs of the Books Written by Alexander Brown.
Additional Related or Separated Material
Related Material
Letters, 1885-1890, from William Cabell, England, to Alexander Brown, are located in the Cabell-Brown Collection within the Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library
Cabell-Brown Papers, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Cabell-Brown Papers, 1885-1890. 12 items. Collection number: Mss. Sm Coll Cabell-Brown
Separated Material
The letters of Alexander Brown have been separated into another inventory located within Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library
Alexander Brown Papers (II), 1748-1900, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Alexander Brown Papers (II), 1748-1900. Collection number: Mss. 65 B86
Microfilm
The letters from Alexander Brown to Charles Deane are located within this collection on microfilm only. The originals are in the Massachusetts Historical Society.
Alexander Brown Papers (1), 1815-1910, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. Alexander Brown Papers (1), 1815-1910. 112 items. Collection number: Mss. Acc.65 B83 microfilm cabinet, drawer 3
Index Terms
Family Names:
Brown family; Cable family
Persons:
Adams, Herbert Baxter, 1850-1901.; Cabell, Mayo.; Curry, J. L. M. (Jabez Lamar Monroe), 1825- 1903.; Deane, Charles, 1813- 1889.; Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1853-1935.
Subjects:
Education--History--Virginia.; Merchants--Virginia--Lynchburg.; Merchants--Virginia--History--19th century.; Plantations--Virginia-- Nelson County.; Women--Education--Virginia.
Corporate Names:
Lynchburg Female Seminary.; Mayo Cabell and Co. (Lynchburg, Va.)
Geographical Names:
Nelson County (Va.)--History--19th century.; Lynchburg (Va.)-- History--19th century.; Virginia--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
Components List
  Series 1: Correspondence of Alexander Brown
- Correspondence of Alexander Brown.
  Items that dealt with, related to or concerned Alexander Brown and the Brown family.
  - Samuel S. Early's correspondence, 1882-1883. (Box-folder 1:1-3)
    These letters deal with the history of the Early family in Virginia and the coats of arms of Capt. John Smith, with several colored sketches.
  - Notification from the American Historical Association, 18 Oct. 1884, and 16 Nov. 1897. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Notification of Brown's having been elected a member of the American Historical Association, signed by Herbert Baxter Adams.
  - Correspondence to Brown from Houghton, Mifflin and Co., Aug. 1895 - 20 Nov. 1895., 3 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Items concern the publication of his book The Cabells and Their Kin.
  - Correspondence with Houghton, Mifflin and Co., 25 June 1889 - 30 June 1891. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence with Houghton, Mifflin and Co., 15 July 1891 - 1 April 1895. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence with Houghton, Mifflin and Co., 26 April 1895 - 14 Feb. 1898. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Letters to Brown from various people, 1876-1885. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Letters from C.H. Bergner. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Letters from D.R. Barton. (Box-folder 1:8)
    - Letters from Wood Bouldin. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Letters to Brown from S.A. Brock, Frank Leslie's Publishing House, New York, NY., 1875. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Letters to Brown from his uncle Andrew Brown, Cooerwull, Bowenfells, Sydney, Australia, 1867-1884. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Letters to Brown from his uncle Andrew Brown, Cooerwull, Bowenfells, Sydney, Australia, 1885-1894. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Letters to Brown from his cousin Charles Bruce, 1875-1876. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Letters to Brown from his sister Cornelia, n.d. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Letters to Brown from Mrs. M.B. Brown, 1876. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Items concern the occasion of the death of his wife.
  - Letters to Brown from various people. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from T.S. Brown, Wales and Luxor, Egypt, 1896. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from Grace F. Brown, 1886. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from J. Thompson Brown, 1876. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from M.B. Brown, n.d. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from his father, R.L Brown, 1874 - 1876. (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Letters from W.F. Butler, 1876. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Letters to Brown from W. Cabell in England, 1883-1884., Postcards. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Letters to Brown from Decatur Axtell, Richmond and Allegheny Railroad Company, 1884-1887. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Items concern Brown's claim against the company.
  - Letters to Brown from Decatur Axtell, C.T. Dabney, and T.C. Eggleston, Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company, 1889. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Items concern Brown's claim against the company for damages inflicted on his property during the floods of 1 June and after.
  - Letters to Brown from correspondents whose names begin with C, n.d. (Box-folder 1:19)
    Some correspondents include Charles Washington Coleman, 20 Feb. 1896, notifying Brown of his election to Phi Beta Kappa; C.B. Clawborne; Fanny Cook; Joseph Cohn; Margaret C. Cabell, N.F. Cabell; and P.H. Cabell.
  - Letters to Brown from various individuals. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Letters from William D. Cabell, 1865-1876. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Letters from Paul C. Callaway. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Letters from J.L. Campbell. (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Letters from W.C. Carrington. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Letters to Brown serving in the Confederate Army, 1861-1866. (Box-folder 1:21)
    There is an afterwards from his grandmother Eliza Callaway.
  - Letters to Brown from various individuals. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Letters from Henry Dreer. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Letters from Dornin & Waldron. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Letters from G.A. Diuguid, an undertaker. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Letters from John Dildine. (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Letters from John W. Daniel. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Letters to Brown from various individuals. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from T. Davis Evans, 1885-1886. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from M.K. Estes, 1875-1876. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from J.J. English. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from Charles Ellis. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from J.C. Echard. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from A.L. Edward. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from C.H. Early. (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Letters from Henry H. Eames. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Letters to Brown from various individuals. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from Thomas P. Kilpatrick, 1876-1881. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from J.N. Gordon. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from James Harvey. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from William W. Hill. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from Charles L. Hill. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from R.A. Coghill. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from Wm.L. Akers. (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Letters from J.D. Horsley, 1893-1898. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Letters to Brown from various individuals. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letters from Richard Irby. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letters from Lee, Seddon & Co. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letters from Lily M. Pleasants. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letters from Daughters of the American Revolution. (Box-folder 1:25)
    - Letters that were unsigned. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Photostats of letters and other items, 1887-1889., 5 letters. Photosats. (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Letters from J.L.M. (Jabez Lamar Monroe) Curry to Alexander Brown., Photostat. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Items concern copies of letters which Brown had ordered.
    - Letter from Brown to Clarence W. Bowen., Photostat. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Items concern dues to the American Historical Association, enclosed in the letter.
    - Unidentified portrait., Photostat. (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Microfilmed letters from Alexander Brown to Charles Deane., 112 items. Microfilmed. (Box-folder 1)
    Originals are located in the Massachusetts Historical Society.
- Papers of Alexander Brown, Justice of the Peace. (Box-folder 2:27)
  These items include the papers of Alexander Brown in his capacity as justice of the peace of Nelson County, Virginia. Included is a notice signed by Alexander Brown Justice of the Peace of Nelson Co. authorizing the patrolling of Negro quarters and other places suspected of unlawful assemblies of slaves, 19 Sept. 1857. [This must be another Alexander Brown as he was only 14 years old at the time].
  Series 2: Business Receipts of Alexander Brown
- Business Receipts of Alexander Brown.
  - Business receipts, 1847-1869. (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Business receipts, 1870-1874. (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Business receipts, 1875. (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Business receipts, 1876. (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Business receipts, 1877. (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Business receipts, 1878. (Box-folder 2:32)
  - Business receipts, 1879. (Box-folder 2:33)
  - Business receipts, 1880. (Box-folder 2:34)
  - Business receipts, 1881. (Box-folder 2:35)
  - Business receipts, 1882. (Box-folder 2:36)
  - Business receipts, 1883. (Box-folder 2:37)
  - Business receipts, 1884. (Box-folder 2:38)
  - Business receipts, 1885. (Box-folder 2:39)
  - Business receipts, 1886-1887. (Box-folder 2:40)
  - Business receipts, 1888-1889. (Box-folder 2:41)
  - Business receipts, 1890-1893. (Box-folder 2:42)
  - Business receipts, 1394-1896. (Box-folder 2:43)
  - Business receipts, 1897-1899. (Box-folder 2:44)
- Business receipts and papers of various members of the Cabell family.
  - Letter of Mrs. Caroline A. Cabell., 1855. (Box-folder 3:45)
  - Business receipts of Mrs. Caroline A. Cabell., 1869-1877. (Box-folder 3:45)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Clifford Cabell, 1852-1864. (Box-folder 3:46)
  - Business receipts of D.S.G. Cabell, 1860-1861. (Box-folder 3:47)
  - Business receipts of Ed. A. Cabell, 1836-1869. (Box-folder 3:48)
  - Business receipts of Edwd. M. Cabell, 1859 - 1879. (Box-folder 3:49)
  - Business receipts of George W. Cabell, 1858. (Box-folder 3:50)
  - Business receipts of Joseph C. Cabell, 1859-1873. (Box-folder 3:51)
  - Business receipts of Lucy G. Cabell, 1875, n.d. (Box-folder 3:52)
- A copy of Littell's Living Age, no. 1840, Sept. 20, 1879. (Box-folder 3:52)
  Series 4: Papers of Mayo Cabell
- Papers of Mayo Cabell.
  - Letters written by Mayo Cabell, 1850-1903. (Box-folder 3:53)
  - Letters written to Mayo Cabell by correspondents, A-C. (Box-folder 3:54)
    Some correspondents include Clifford Cabell, A letter, 29 July 1867, from L. M. Blackford, N.Y., commenting on the attitude of the Radicals and a letter, 17 Jan. 1849, from Wm. M. Cabell to his uncle Mayo Cabell commenting on Louis Napoleon's election to the Presidency of France and on the California gold rush
  - Letters written to Mayo Cabell by correspondents, D-L. (Box-folder 3:55)
    Some items included are a letter, 23 April 1864, from Jno. H. Daniell, a Confederate soldier in Early's Division to Mayo Cabell and letters, 20 Sept. 1867 and 10 Jan. 1868, from Thomas W. Gilmer, Fredericksburg, to Mayo Cabell about Texas land values.
  - Letter written to Mayo Cabell by correspondents, M. (Box-folder 3:56)
    Some items included are a letter, 29 April 1865, from Martin & Cardoza, Richmond, Virginia to Mayo Cabell reporting damage in the burning of Richmond.
  - Letters written to Mayo Cabell by correspondents, P. (Box-folder 3:57)
  - Letters written to Mayo Cabell by correspondents, R-W. (Box-folder 3:58)
  - Legal documents and business papers of Mayo Cabell. (Box-folder 3:59)
  - Account of Mayo Cabell with Isaac R. Watkins. (Box-folder 3:60)
  Series 5: Papers concerning the books written by Alexander Brown
- Papers concerning the books written by Alexander Brown.
  - Notes used by Brown for The Genesis, The First Republic, and The Cabells and Their Kin. (Box-folder 4:61-62)
  - Scrapbook. (Box-folder 4:63)
    Scrapbook contains reviews of The Genesis of the United States, and the author's reply to critics of The First Republic in America, as well as newspaper clippings of reviews of his books.
  - Clippings concerning the reviews of books. (Box-folder 4:64)
  - Notes taken by Brown for his books. (Box-folder 4:65)
    Included in these items are autobiographical notes on Brown.
  - Miscellaneous papers of Brown. (Box-folder 4:66)
  - List of subscribers to Brown's books. (Box-folder 4:67)
  - Brown manuscript about Colonial Virginia. (Box-folder 4:68)
  - Brown's notes and manuscripts about Colonial Virginia. (Box-folder 4:69)
  - Printed copy of Brown's, The History of Our Earliest History. (Box-folder 4:70)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings. (Box-folder 4:70)
  Series 6: Bills, receipts and papers of Mayo Cabell and his son
- Bills, receipts and papers of Mayo Cabell and his son.
  - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1816-1869, n.d.
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1816-1839. (Box-folder 5:71)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1840-1849. (Box-folder 5:72)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1850-1853. (Box-folder 5:73)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1854. (Box-folder 5:74)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1855. (Box-folder 5:75)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1856. (Box-folder 5:76)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1857. (Box-folder 5:77)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1858-1859. (Box-folder 5:78)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1860-1861. (Box-folder 5:79)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1862-1864. (Box-folder 5:80)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1865-1868. (Box-folder 5:81)
    - Bills and receipts of Mayo Cabell, 1869, n.d. (Box-folder 5:82)
  - Miscellaneous receipts and letters of Mayo Cabell. (Box-folder 5:83)
  - Receipts and letters to William M. Cabell and William D. Cabell, ca. 1850. (Box-folder 5:84)
    Items include four letters, 1852 and 1853, from Mayo Cabell to his son William D. Cabell, a student at the University of Virginia.
  - Bills and receipts of William Cabell, 1846-1900. (Box-folder 5:85)
  Series 7: Correspondence of Alexander Brown
- Correspondence of Alexander Brown.
  - Letters written to Brown from the President of the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences, 1891. (Box-folder 6:86)
    Items were written upon Brown's election to membership.
  - Business letters from Henry Loving & Son, Richmond, Virginia. (Box-folder 6:86)
  - Business letters from Taliaferro & Loving, Richmond, Virginia. (Box-folder 6:86)
  - Letters from the Maine Historical Society, 1892. (Box-folder 6:87)
    Letters concern notification of membership and general correspondence.
  - Letters from the Massachusetts Historical Society, 1891. (Box-folder 6:87)
  - Letters from the Maryland Historical Society, 1881. (Box-folder 6:87)
  - Letters from the New England Historic Genealogical Society, 1880. (Box-folder 6:88)
    Letters concern confirmation of membership onto Brown; and legal and business correspondence.
  - Letter from Alexander Rives, Charlottesville, Virginia, 20 Dec. 1875. (Box-folder 6:89)
    Letter concerns rumors of Brown's political activities while serving as postmaster.
  - Letter, 1887. (Box-folder 6:89)
    Letter informs Brown that he has been elected as a fellow of the Royal Historical Society.
  - General business correspondence. (Box-folder 6:90)
  - Charter membership certificate of the Sons of the American Revolution, 25 March 1891. (Box-folder 6:90)
  - Correspondence regarding historical matters. (Box-folder 6:90)
  - Letters relating to mining in Virginia and Texas land. (Box-folder 6:91)
  - Letters from Lyon G. Tyler, 12 Oct. 1900 and 15 May 1901., 2 letters. (Box-folder 6:91)
    Letters concern notification of Brown of the Doctor of Laws degree awarded him by the College of William and Mary.
  - Letters from J.W. Tyson of Baltimore and Marietta, Georgia, 1877. (Box-folder 6:93)
    Letters are in regards to copper mining and property.
  - Letters from J.W. Tyson. (Box-folder 6:93)
    Letters include one, 28 Dec. 1876, regarding a country estate, mining property, and the proposed Clifton Forge Railroad to connect the canal and Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad.
  - Letters from J.W. Tyson, 1879. (Box-folder 6:94)
    Letters mostly concerning mining.
  - Letters from J.W. Tyson, 1880-1881. (Box-folder 6:95)
  - Letters from J.W. Tyson, 1878. (Box-folder 6:96)
  - Miscellaneous letters about genealogical researches and business interests, 1887,1881, and 1894. (Box-folder 6:97)
    Among the correspondents is William C. Rives of Cobham, Virginia, Newport, Rhode Island, and Washington, D.C.
  - Letters notifying Brown of membership in the Virginia Historical Society, 1878, 1881, and 1894. (Box-folder 6:97)
  Series 8: Miscellaneous Materials
- Miscellaneous materials of Alexander Brown.
  - Items concerning the paper, New Views of Early Virginia History,1606-1619.
    - Printed copy of Brown's paper, New Views of Early Virginia History,1606-1619. (Box-folder 7:98)
      Item includes corrections by the author.
    - Letters from Brown to Robert L. Taylor., 2 letters. (Box-folder 7:98)
      Items concern Taylor's purchase of Brown's paper, New Views of Early Virginia History,1606-1619.
  - Copy of The Richmond Dispatch, 14 Dec. 1894., Copy. (Box-folder 7:98)
  - Newspaper clippings. (Box-folder 7:98)
  - A printed copy of A Church Calendar. (Box-folder 7:98)
  - Printed picture of Sir Edwyn Sandys., Printed picture. (Box-folder 7:99)
  - Photographs.
    - Photograph of Rev. Robert J. Breckinridge., Photograph. (Box-folder 7:99)
    - Photograph of Ladies of the Norwood Institute, 1895., Photograph. (Box-folder 7:99)
    - Photograph of Wm. Wirt Henry., Photograph. (Box-folder 7:99)
    - Photograph of Rev. John Breckinridge., Photograph. (Box-folder 7:99)
  - Miscellaneous articles and printed matter. (Box-folder 7:99)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Brown, ca. 1873. (Box-folder 7:100)
    Items include legal papers regarding Brown's being adjudged bankrupt, 1873.
  - Letter from Mrs.Caroline A. Cabell. (Box-folder 7:100)
    Letter concerns Mrs. Caroline A. Cabell, giving consent to Brown's marriage with her daughter Kate.
  - Letters of condolence, 1880., 2 items. (Box-folder 7:100)
    Letters were written to Brown upon the occasion of his father's death.
  - Papers relating to Alexander Brown, Jr., 1869-1875. (Box-folder 7:101)
    Items concern the administering of the estate of Mrs. Lucy S. Brown.
- Geological survey map of Nelson and Amherst counties, ca. 1878. (Box-folder 7:102)
- Field notes of land surveyed from N. Francis Cabell and John W. Mosby, 6 Feb. 1851. (Box-folder 7:102)
- Small volumes of miscellaneous entries., 4 items. (Box-folder 7:102)
- Church subscription list for the Rev. T.D. Godwin, 1847. (Box-folder 8:103)
- Itemized accounts of Dr. Paul C. Callaway for medical services to a family, 1855-1857. (Box-folder 8:103)
- Receipts. (Box-folder 8:103)
- Business receipts of Alexander Brown. (Box-folder 8:104)
- List of Confederate bonds, 16 July 1864. (Box-folder 8:105)
  Bonds were held by P.A. Gilmer for produce sold to the Army.
- List of clothes needed for slaves, 1847. (Box-folder 8:105)
  List details winter clothes needed for 62 slaves, 8 house servants, and 54 field hands.
- Letter from a Nacogdoches, Texas law firm, 1852. (Box-folder 8:105)
  Letter from the Nacogdoches, Texas law firm regarding lands held by a group of Virginians.
- Business papers. (Box-folder 8:106)
  Papers include those of Capt. Paul Stratton and others.
- Notebook of A.M. Morrell of Norwood High School, 1872-1873. (Box-folder 8:107)
  Notebook contains questions relating to history kept by A.M. Morrell of Norwood High School.
- Letters and postcards from Edgar Whitehead regarding tin mining, 1880's and 1890's. (Box-folder 8:108)
  Letters and postcards are from Edgar Whitehead, Amherst Court House, regarding tin mining with references to Boise, Idaho, western lands, and climate.
- Memorandum of agreement between Alexander Brown and Houghton, Mifflin and Co. (Box-folder 8:109)
  Item regards Brown's book The First Republic in America.
- Letters from Charles L. Woodward, dealer in Rare Books and Pamphlets, New York, New York. (Box-folder 8:109)
  Series 9:Papers of Alexander Brown
- Papers of Alexander Brown.
  - Brown family letters and receipts. (Box-folder 9:110)
  - Brown family letters and receipts. (Box-folder 9:111)
  - Letters written by Alexander Brown. (Box-folder 9:112)
  - Receipts from publishing companies and historical societies. (Box-folder 9:113)
  - Receipts from publishing companies and historical societies. (Box-folder 9:114)
  - Bills, receipts, and envelopes. (Box-folder 9:115)
- Ledger of Mayo Cabell and Company, a lumber firm in Lynchburg, Virginia, 1855-1856. (Oversize MsV. 5)
  The inside cover of the ledger lists the terms of the partnership and distributor in Richmond, Virginia.
- Account book of Norwood Plantation, Nelson County, Virginia, Feb. - June 1867. (Oversize MsV. 6)
- Surveys and charts probably made by Alexander Brown., Rolled up papers. (Oversize See Oversize File.)
- Six photographs of member of the Brown family in Australia., Photographs.; 6 items. (Oversize See Photographs in oversize file.)
  Series 10: Papers of R. L. Brown, the son of Alexander Brown
- Papers of R. L. Brown, the son of Alexander Brown, 1842-1870, n.d.
  - Manuscript volume containing the accounts of Robert L. Brown, 1842-1860., Approximately 400 pages. MsV. 7 (Box 10)
  - Manuscript volume containing the accounts of "Belmont" and "Benvenue" plantations, 1843-1864., Approximately 230 pages. MsV. 8 (Box 10)